A Finding Aid to the Martin Johnson Heade Papers, 1853-1904, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Martin Johnson Heade papers
1853-1904
Archives of American Art
Heade, Martin Johnson, 1819-1904
AAA.headmart
Archival Resource Key
0.4 Linear feet
The scattered papers of painter Martin Johnson Heade measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1853 to 1904. The bulk of the collection consists of letters from his friend and fellow artist, Frederic Edwin Church between 1866-1899. Within the papers is an annotated sketchbook, circa 1853-1877, and a detailed handwritten notebook about hummingbirds dating from circa 1864 and circa 1881. Also found are a few letters and notes from others, deeds, and an 1865 exhibition catalog.
Biographical Note
Martin Johnson Heade was born in Lumberville, Pennsylvania, in 1819. He studied art under painter Edward Hicks, and began his career as a portrait painter. After traveling abroad and living in Rome for two years, he made his artistic debut in 1841 at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts. Heade began exhibiting regularly in 1848, after another trip to Europe, and became an itinerant artist until he settled in New York in 1859. In the early 1860s he turned to painting landscapes and seascapes, in which he could explore spatial structure and the effects of light. During this period he became friends with fellow landscape painter, Frederic Edwin Church, one of his few friends in the art world, and with whom he exchanged letters for over thirty years. Besides landscapes, Heade painted many still-lifes of flowers. After trips to South and Central America in 1863-1864, 1866, and 1870, he began painting hummingbirds and orchids in tropical settings. Heade was never fully accepted by the New York art establishment and for a period of time resumed his itinerant lifestyle. In 1883 he settled in Saint Augustine, Florida and married. He also found a patron, Henry Morrison Flagler, to commission his work, and continued to paint still-lifes, swamp scenes, and hummingbirds, until his death in 1904.
Scope and Content Note
The scattered papers of painter Martin Johnson Heade measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1853 to 1904. the bulk of the collection consists of letters from his friend and fellow artist, Frederic Edwin Church between 1866-1899. Within the papers is an annotated sketchbook, circa 1853-1877, and a detailed handwritten notebook about hummingbirds dating from circa 1864 and circa 1881. Also found are a few letters and notes from others, deeds, and an 1865 exhibition catalog.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection, items are arranged by type of material into folders. Within each folder, items are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Related material found in the Archives includes a Martin Johnson Heade letter to Frederic Edwin Church, 1868, and the microfilm of a loan of Martin Johnson Heade papers housed at the Bucks County Historical Society containing biographical material about Heade, available on reel 4408. Originals are located at Bucks County Historical Society.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 1955 by Robert McIntyre, art historian and director of the Macbeth Gallery.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Martin Johnson Heade in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2007, and total 214 images.
Painters -- Florida; Hummingbirds; Painting -- United States; Sketchbooks; Church, Frederic Edwin, 1826-1900
- Martin Johnson Heade papers, circa 1853-1904; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The collection consists of forty letters, some illustrated, from Frederic Church discussing his paintings, his studio, trips abroad to Rome, Syria, and Mexico, his health and his family, and other artists. Church also responds to Heade's letters and provides advice on various subjects. Letters from others include a letter expressing thanks from May Camphen and a letter from the Illinois Audubon Society to the Estate of Martin Johnson Heade requesting a likeness of Mr. Heade for their collection. Also found is a note of praise to Sarita Brady. Within the papers is an annotated sketchbook by Heade containing pencil drawings of animals and landscapes as well as a few notes on art and his travels to South America and a detailed handwritten notebook that includes an essay and other notes on hummingbirds. Miscellaneous papers include deeds for Heade's property in Chicago, Illinois, and an 1865 catalog for the "Exhibition of the Royal Academy of Arts" in which Heade exhibited.
  - Letters from Frederic Edwin Church, 1866-1868; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Frederic Edwin Church, 1869-1871; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Frederic Edwin Church, 1873-1878; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Frederic Edwin Church, 1880-1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Frederic Edwin Church, 1885-1899; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from others, 1900-1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Note to Sarita Brady, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annotated Sketchbook, circa 1853-1877; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notebook on Hummingbirds, circa 1881; circa 1864; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Scope and Contents
    This notebook contains a draft introduction to "Gems of Brazil" which would have been written circa 1864, following a trip to Brazil. Heade left Brazil for London in early 1864, where he tried to publish his book, but abandoned the idea and left England in 1865. Entries later in the notebook, including references to "game monopolies" and painting sales, seem related to events in 1881.
  - Deeds, 1853-1855; 1876; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Catalog, "The Exhibition of the Royal Academy of Arts", 1865; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)